Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 27: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 27; 148 folios 1 col. [fols. 5r-131v], 23 lines; 2 col. [fols. 132-145], 23 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Twelve miniatures. Leather case. Glossy wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Rebound with machine-made t
  Illustrations: Fol. 146v: Two drawings. First drawing of David: anointed. David in middle, servant on left holding the cup, Samuel on right anointing. Captions from left to right "servant," "David," and "Samuel, prophet of God, anoints David for his kingship." Second drawing of David: as musician. He is playing the harp while a servant looks on from the left.
  Illustration: Fol. 147r: Drawing of Ethiopian church singers with musical instruments. Caption: "These scholars sing for Abba Yohannəs, who finished his [spiritual] combat with patience."
  Illustration: Fol. 147v: Drawing of the Virgin Mary with the Christ Child and Archangels Michael (left) and Gabriel (right). Caption from left to right: " Saint Mika'el," "With Her Beloved Son," and "Saint Gäbrə'el."
  Illustration: Fol. 148r: Drawing of Saint George: slaying the dragon. Caption: "Saint Giyorgis."
  Fols. 1r, 148v: Pen trial and in crude, later hand, a note of ownership: "This Psalter belongs to Wäsäne."
  Fol. 1v: In crude, later hand, a note of ownership: "This Psalter belongs to Wäsäne."
  Fol. 145r: Pen trial in pencil and ink (introductory hymn for Psalter).
  Fol. 146r: Notes of the later transaction of this manuscript. A seller's name is mentioned: Alläqqa Tädlä; a buyer's name is mentioned: Ato Awəgəčäw.
  - Excerpt from the Psalter of the Virgin, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r. (Unitid 27)
    In another hand.
  - Excerpts from the Ordinary Prayer of the Mass, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1v. (Unitid 27)
  - Morning Prayer, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 4r. (Unitid 27)
    In Amharic in another hand in purple ink and pencil.
  - Psalms, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 5r-113r. (Unitid 27)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 113v-125r. (Unitid 27)
  - Song of Songs, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 125v-131v. (Unitid 27)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 132r-141r. (Unitid 27)
    - Monday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 132rv. (Unitid 27)
    - Tuesday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 132v-134r. (Unitid 27)
    - Wednesday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 134r-136r. (Unitid 27)
    - Thursday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 136r-137v. (Unitid 27)
    - Friday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 137v-139r. (Unitid 27)
    - Saturday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 139r-140r. (Unitid 27)
    - Sunday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 140r-141r. (Unitid 27)
  - Gate of Light, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 141r-145r. (Unitid 27)
  - List of Šäwa Kings, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 145v-146r. (Unitid 27)
    In crude, later hand.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 28: Psalter. Dawit, 1900s; 28; 76 folios 1 col. [1r-59r], 24 lines; 2 col. [59r-75v], 24 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Eleven miniatures. Leather case. Wooden boards, lower stamped red leather board is original to the manuscript, upper board is leather and newer. Stitched and partially open spine. The first half of the Psalter is missing and the first quire has folios out of sequence. The whole has unrelated miniatures painted over text (probably to increase its sales value). Fol. 1r: Text erased (originally was the beginning of Psalm 91) to disguise that the book was divided into half (probably for the market). Fol. 1r, 76rv: Blank. 12 x 16.5 cm (Unitid 28)
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Miniature of the Holy Trinity seated with one garment.
  Illustration: Fol. 8v: Miniature of Saint George slaying the Dragon.
  Illustration: Fol. 16v: Miniature of the Virgin Mary with the Christ Child and angels with drawn swords.
  Illustration: Fol. 24v: Miniature of Christ: Crowned with Thorns, and Jews with swords on his left and right.
  Illustration: Fol. 32v: Miniature of the Christ: Crucifixion: One Cross, with the Virgin Mary and John the Evangelist and other women.
  Illustration: Fol. 40v: Miniature of Virgin Mary with her parents Joachim and Hannah (Anna).
  Illustration: Fols. 43r, 59r: Häräg.
  Illustration: Fol. 48r: Miniature of Christ with the Apostle Peter.
  Illustration: Fol. 56v: Miniature of Christ Raising Adam and Eve to Paradise.
  Illustration: Fol. 64v: Miniature of Christ between two kings.
  Illustration: Fol. 75r: Miniature of Christ: Ascension, surrounded by angels.
  Gift of Bruce Willsie, Princeton Class of 1986.
  - Psalms, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-43r. (Unitid 28)
    Incomplete at the beginning, starts with the end of Psalm 91. Psalm 118 does include additions about the spiritual meanings of the Hebrew Alphabet.
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 43r-53r. (Unitid 28)
  - Song of Songs, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 53r-59r. (Unitid 28)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 59r-69v. (Unitid 28)
    - Monday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 59r-60r. (Unitid 28)
    - Tuesday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 60r-62r. (Unitid 28)
    - Wednesday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 62r-63v. (Unitid 28)
    - Thursday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 63v-66r. (Unitid 28)
    - Friday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 66r-67v. (Unitid 28)
    - Saturday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 67v-68v. (Unitid 28)
    - Sunday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 68v-69v. (Unitid 28)
  - Gate of Light, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 69v-74v. (Unitid 28)
  - Magical Prayer Against Snakes, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 74v. (Unitid 28)
    In another trained hand.
  - Image of the Savior of the World, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 75v. (Unitid 28)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 30: Homily [in Honor] of [the Archangel] Michael (Dərəsanä Mika'el), circa 1770-1959; 30; 108 folios 2 cols., 19-24 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Leather case. Glossy wooden upper boards, plain wooden board used to mend original lower board; stitched and open spine. Fols. 1r-3v: Blank 17 x 22.5 cm (Unitid 30)
  Fols. 10v, 11rv, 12v, passim: The owner's names Haylä Maryam and Wälätä Maryam appear at the beginning and ending of every text.
  Fols. 9v, 11rv, 12v, passim: The scribe's name Wäldä Eləyas appears at the beginning and ending of every text.
  Fols. 105rv: Pen trial.
  Late 18th century with 20th-century additions.
  References: See references for manuscript no. 21.
  - Hədar, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-12v. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily by Dämatewos, Bishop of Alexandria, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-10v. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 10v-11v. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission to Joshua, Son of Nun, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 11v-12v. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 12v. (Unitid 30)
  - Tahəśaś, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 12v-19v. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 12v-18r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 18r-19r. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Rescue the Three Holy Children, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 19rv. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 19v. (Unitid 30)
  - Tərr, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 19v-29v. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily, Author Not Given, late 1700s>, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 21v-24r. (Unitid 30)
  - Tərr, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 14v-21v. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 25r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily on the Glory of St Michael the Archangel, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 19v-28v. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 28v-29v. (Unitid 30)
  - Yäkkatit, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 29v-35r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 29v-33r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 33r-34v. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Samson, the Giant, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 34v. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 34v-35r. (Unitid 30)
  - Mäggabit, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 35r-52r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily by the Archbishop of Antioch, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 35r-49v. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 49v-51v. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Balaam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 51v-52r. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 52r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miyazya, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 52r-61r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 52r-57r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 57r-60r. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary entries: Mission of the Archangel to the Prophet Jeremiah, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 60r-61r. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 61r. (Unitid 30)
  - Gənbot, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 61r-66r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily by Yohannəs, Bishop of Ethiopia, Who Came After Bishop Yəśhaq, on the Conflict Between the Consort of King Arqadewos and John Chysostom, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 61r-62v. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 62v-65v. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission of the Archangel to Habakkuk, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 65v-66r. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 66r. (Unitid 30)
  - Säne, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 66r-77r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily on the Family of Astäraniqos and Euphemia, by Yohannəs, Bishop of Aksum, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 66r-72v. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 73r-75v. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary entry: the Building of the Church of the Archangel in Place of a Pagan Temple in Alexandria, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 75v-77r. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 77r. (Unitid 30)
  - Hamle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 77v-85v. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily on the Wicked Wealthy Man Whose Property Was Inherited by the Son of His Poor Neighbor [by Bishop Yohannəs], late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 77v-82r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 82r-84v. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission to the Camp of Sennacherib, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 84v-85r. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 85v. (Unitid 30)
  - Nähase, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 85v-95v. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily on the Book of the Angels that Came from Jerusalem, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 85v-89r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 89r-95r. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission of the Archangel to the Emperor Constantine, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 95rv. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 95v. (Unitid 30)
  - Mäskäräm, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 95v-99v. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily on Not Worshipping Other Gods, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 95v-98r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 98r-99r. (Unitid 30)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission to Prophet Isaiah, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 99rv. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 99v. (Unitid 30)
  - Təqəmt, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 99v-107r. (Unitid 30)
  - Homily on the Need to Make the Angels Sureties by Honoring Them, Author Not Given, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 99v-103r. (Unitid 30)
  - Miracle, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 103r-106v. (Unitid 30)
  - Excerpt from Daily Prayer, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 105v. (Unitid 30)
    In a later hand.
  - Synaxary entry: Mission to Prophet Samuel, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 106v-107r. (Unitid 30)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, late 18th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 107r. (Unitid 30)
  - Poem, 1959 August; multiple folios; Located on folio 108rv. (Unitid 30)
    In later hand, a poem and a note in Amharic in green pen, largely illegible dated "30/12/52" EC [August 1959 AD].
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 31: Antiphonary of the Church (Mə'əraf), 1900s; 31; 54 folios 2 cols., 23 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Plain wooden boards, stitched and open spine, deteriorated binding. Fols. 1 and 2: cut and detached from the quire. Fol. 54v: Blank 12 x 16 cm (Unitid 31)
  Musical notation system used throughout. Small hand.
  References: Mə'əraf is one of the five books in the collection Amməstu säwatəwä zemawoč, the Ethiopic divine office and indispensible to the performance for the office (therefore common not proper). This manuscript includes a selection of Psalms, daily office prayers, Mystagogia, and "school chants." See Aethiopica Encyclopedia, vol. 3, p. 910: For information on Mə'əraf chants, see Bernard Velat's Etudes sur le Me'eraf (Paris: 1966), vols 1 and 2.
  - Mə'əraf (Incomplete At the Beginning), 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-54r. (Unitid 31)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 32: Sword of the Trinity (Säyəfä Səlasse), Sword of the Divinity (Säyəfä Mäläkot), Image of the Trinity (Mälkə'a Səlasse), 1900s; 32; 104 folios 1 col., 14 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No miniatures. No case. Wooden boards covered with red stamped leather, stitched and covered binding. Fols. 1r, 4v, 102v-104r: Blank 10 x 14.5 cm (Unitid 32)
  Illustrations: Fols. 5r, 19v, 30r, 38v, 63r, 72r, 88v: Häräg with angels.
  Fols. 9v, 55r, 26r, 77r, 88r, 102r: Owner's name Habtä Maryam Täfära appears in original text.
  Fols. 102r: Scribe's name Wäldä Maryam appears in original text.
  Fols. 102r: The owner of the manuscript has had listed his wife and children's baptismal names (in the same hand as the manuscript).
  Illustration: Fol. 104v: Crude drawing of angel.
  References: Regarding Sword of the Trinity, see Conti Rossini, Notice, no. 106; Strelcyn, Lincei, no. 53 and 62; Säyəfä Səlasse Wä-Mälkə'a Səlasse, Täsfa Press, Addis Ababa 1947 EC. Regarding Sword of the Divinity, see also Chaîne, "Répertoire," No. 20. See also references listed in manuscript no. 7, 13.
  - Sword of the Trinity, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 5r-84r. (Unitid 32)
    - Introductory Homily, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 5r-9v. (Unitid 32)
    - Mə'əraf (Incomplete At the Beginning), 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 10r-19r. (Unitid 32)
    - Monday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-54r. (Unitid 32)
    - Tuesday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 19v-29v. (Unitid 32)
    - Wednesday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 30r-38r. (Unitid 32)
    - Thursday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 38v-50r. (Unitid 32)
    - Friday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 50r-62v. (Unitid 32)
    - Saturday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 63r-71v. (Unitid 32)
    - Sunday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 72r-78r. (Unitid 32)
    - Readings for Any Day, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 78r-84r. (Unitid 32)
  - Sword of the Divinity, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 84r-88r. (Unitid 32)
  - Image of the Trinity, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 88v-102r. (Unitid 32)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 33: Prayer of Peter (Sälotä Petros), Prayer of Mary At Golgotha (Zä-Säne Golgota), Mystagogia (Təməhrətä Həbu'a), early 20th century; 33; 142 folios 1 cols., 12 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Plain wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Fols. 1r-4v,140v-142v: Blank 6.5 x 9 cm (Unitid 33)
  Illustrations: Fols. 5r, 20v, 23v, 29r, 47r, 68r, 100r, 103v, 131r: Häräg.
  Illustration: Fol. 81v: Magical charts based on the name of Ananəya, one of the three holy children rescued from the furnace.
  Fols. 9r, 10r, 12rv, 16rv, 17v passim: The owner's name, Wäldä Maryam, appears at the end of every prayer.
  Part of the seal states in Ge'ez "Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah. Menelik the King of Kings of Ethiopia."
  Fols. 14v, 24v, 34v, 44v, 54v, 64v, 74v, 84v, 94v, 103r, 113r, 123r, 133r: Quires are marked with Ethiopic numerals: quire 1, 2, etc.
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 7, 11, 13.
  - Prayer of Peter, Sälotä Petros, early 20th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 5r-99v. (Unitid 33)
    Fol. 35r: The daily readings were marked but erased (except on this folio) on the relevant pages at the top of the folio.
  - Prayer of Mary At Golgotha, Zä-Säne Golgota, early 20th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 100r-130v. (Unitid 33)
  - Mystagogia, Təməhrətä Həbu'at, early 20th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 131r-139v. (Unitid 33)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 34: Seal of Emperor Menelik II, circa 1870-1930; 34; 1 folio Paper 25 x 29 cm (Unitid 34)
  Illustration: In gold on a red background, a seal with the crowned lion of the tribe of Judah carrying a cross inside a circle with sun rays and Ge'ez words. Part of the seal states in Ge'ez "Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah. Menelik the King of Kings of Ethiopia."
  Loose folio: On green paper "1907 A merry Christmas and a happy 1908 New-year to Rob." Then, "from Enno Littmann" and "Seal of Menilek II Inscription: Prevailed hath the Lion of the tribe of Judah! Menilik [sic] the king of Kings of Ethiopia."
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 35: Seal of Däjazmač Gäbrä Selassə, circa 1870-1930; 35; 1 folio Paper 25 x 29 cm (Unitid 35)
  Illustration: In gold on green background, a seal with a cross inside of a star of David inside a circle with Ge'ez words.
  Part of the seal states in Ge'ez "Däjazmač Gäbrä Səlasse of T. M. A." TMA is an abbreviation meaning he was the governor of Tigre, Marb, and Adua Provinces. For information about this governor (d. 1931), see his entry in Aethiopica Encyclopedia, vol. 2, p. 628."
  Loose folio: On green paper "Seal of Dadjazmatch Gabra Sellese. Inscription: Gabra Sellase the governor of Tigre of the province of the Marab and of Adua."
  References: See references listed in manuscript no.34.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 36, 1700s; 36; 52 folios 1 col. and 2 col. (see notes below). Parchment Codex. Varied lines per page: Written in black and red ink. No case. Glossy wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Original binding missing, machine-made twine used. The quires of the book were mis-ordered in binding the book, so that the same text is not continuous. In the cases of Image of Täklä Haymanot and Prayer of Mary at Golgotha, the beginning folios of each appears last. 11 x 19 cm (Unitid 36)
  : Image of Täklä Haymanot, Prayer of Mary At Golgotha, Image of Paul and Peter, Image of the Trinity, Prayer of the Covenant, Hymns for the Passion of Christ. Mälkə'a Täklä Haymanot, Zä-Säne Golgota, Mälkə'a Petəros Wa Pawəlos, Mälkə'a Selassie, Sälotä Kidan, Mälkə'a Həmamat
  Fol. 1r: Pen trial.
  Fols. 11v, 27r: Owner's name listed as Kidanä Wäld.
  Fol. 27r: Scribe's name is listed as Habtä Maryam.
  Fol. 50v: Colophon is not original to manuscript, the manuscript itself dates to earlier than late 1800s and appears to be from the 1700s.
  Fols. 50v: In a different hand, at the bottom of the second column, after a horizontal line: "In this year of Luke [the Evangelist] 7399 EC [sic] Year of Creation, on the 18th day of the month of Təqəmt, at the 11th hour, the earthquake happened [lit. the earth was shaken]. On the 13th day of the month of Hədar (on the second night of the moon), [the body of] Dägač Nadäw was transferred [i.e. moved by the family]. It was 21 years ago that he died." The year of creation 7399 is 1899 AD. The year of Dägač Nadäw's death is 1888 AD. On the military commander and close associate of Menelik II, Dägač Nadäw, see the Aethiopica Encyclopedia entry, vol. 3, p 1093.
  Fol. 52r: Pencil scrawls. In a later hand, someone tried to write "Abətä Yohanäs [sic] the apostle."
  Handwritten letters in Ge'ez to Enno Littman, enclosed in archival slip The letter marked "(a)" is from Yirdaw, brother of Kidanä Wäld, and it starts: "O Dr. Littman, scholar and wise man, I received your letter and I took seven francs from the German consulate. I have so many things I want to say to you because you are faithful in small things. Said by Yirdaw, brother of Kidanä Wäld, Written in Holy Jerusalem, on 12 of the month of Təqəmt." The letter marked (b) is from Kidanä Wäld, brother of Yirdaw. It says: "O Dr. Littman, full of new wisdom, I received your letter, with powerful words even though the size is small. I took the money [you sent] from Hannah Faris, which is 30 francs. May God protect you in your going out and your coming in forever... I have so many things I want to say to you because you are faithful in small things. Said by Kidanä Wäld, brother of Yirdaw. Written in Holy Jerusalem, on 12 of the month of Təqəmt."
  Gift of Enno Littmann.
  See references listed in manuscript no. 7 and 11. Regarding Prayer of the Covenant, Velat, Me'eraf vol. 1, pp. 1–6; and (tr.) Velat, Me'eraf II, pp.170–74; Sebastian Euringer, "Übersetzung der 'Preces officii matutini' in Dillmann's 'Chrestomathia Aethiopica,'" Orientalia, NS, vol. 11 (1942), pp. 333–66; and Daoud–Mersie, Liturgy, pp. 314–21.
  - List of Marian Feasts (1 Col.), 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1v, 12r. (Unitid 36)
  - Image of Täklä Haymanot, Mälkə'a Täklä Haymanot (2 Col.), 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r-6v, 9r-11v, 18r-20v, 33rv, 34rv. (Unitid 36)
    (Chaîne, "Répertoire," No. 211)
  - Prayer of Mary At Golgotha, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 4r-8v, 11v, 16rv, 21rv, 25rv, 27r, 28r-30v, 35r-37v. (Unitid 36)
    (2 Col.)
  - Image of Paul and Peter, Mälkə'a Petəros Wa Pawəlos, 1700s; multiple folios; Located on folio 12rv, 17rv, 26rv, 31r-32v, 34r, 39rv. (Unitid 36)
    (1 Col.)
    (Chaîne, "Répertoire," 187)